Taisiya Glushkova

Home page / Google Scholar / Semantic Scholar / Github / Twitter / LinkedIn glushkovato@gmail.com

I'm a PhD student at SARDINE lab at Instituto Superior Técnico, supervised by André F. T. Martins and Chrysoula Zerva. I am broadly interested in language representations, NLP evaluation, interpretability and uncertainty estimation. Currently working on Machine Translation (MT) evaluation, aiming to create more trustworthy systems which are robust to the variation observed across different languages and domains. Based in Lisbon, Portugal.

Education

PhD student in Computer Science, Instituto Superior Técnico

Lisbon, Portugal 2020 - present

Computer Science and Engineering Department; Supervisor: André F. T. Martins

Thesis title: Uncertainty Estimation and Robustness in Machine Translation Evaluation

Collaborative project MAIA (Multilingual AI Agent Assistants) in the Carnegie Mellon Portugal Program partnership involving Instituto de Telecomunicações, INESC-ID, Carnegie Mellon University and Unbabel.

Collaborative project NextGenAl (Center for Responsible Al).

Research interests: uncertainty estimation, interpretability and robustness of machine translation evaluation

MSc in Data Science, HSE University

Moscow, Russia

Computer Science Department; Supervisor: Ekaterina Artemova

2018 - 2020

BSc in Applied Mathematics and Computer Science, HSE University

Moscow, Russia

Computer Science Department; Supervisor: Ekaterina Artemova

2014 - 2018

Experience

Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, USA

Research Internship

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

Robust and interpretable machine translation evaluation. Supervisor: Alon Lavie.

Instituto Superior Técnico

Lisbon, Portugal

PhD Researcher

Sep 2020 - present

• Uncertainty estimation for machine translation evaluation.

HSE University

Moscow, Russia

Research Internship (Part-time)

Oct 2019 - Aug 2020

• Question-answering for Russian language.

Unbabel Applied Al Research Summer Internship

Lisbon, Portugal Jul 2019 - Oct 2019

• Language model-based data filtering and selection for machine translation.

Digital Decisions

Moscow, Russia

Data Scientist

Feb 2019 - Mar 2020

- Hierarchical classification and routing of the customers messages.
- Named entity recognition for a speech assistant.

Diginetica

Yandex

Moscow, Russia

Junior Data Scientist/Engineer

Jun 2017 - Dec 2017

- Spell checker tool for search queries aimed to suggest synonymous corrections for misspelled words.
- Snippets from product reviews: extraction of ultra-concise summaries of opinions over products.

Python Software Engineering Internship

Moscow, Russia

Summer 2015

• Analysis of the personalities in the flow of search queries.

• Marking and classification of multiple object definitions, ranking them in order of relevance for users.

Selected Publications

BLEU Meets COMET: Combining Lexical and Neural Metrics Towards Robust Machine Translation Evaluation Taisiya Glushkova, Chrysoula Zerva, André F. T. Martins [ACL Anthology, poster] **EAMT 2023**

Disentangling Uncertainty in Machine Translation Evaluation Chrysoula Zerva, Taisiya Glushkova , Ricardo Rei, André F. T. Martins EMNLP 2022		[ACL Anthology, poster]
Uncertainty-Aware Machine Translation Evaluation Taisiya Glushkova, Chrysoula Zerva, Ricardo Rei, André F. T. Martins Presented at the Sixth Conference on Machine Translation (WMT21) at EMNLP 2021 EMNLP Findings 2021		[ACL Anthology, slides]
	bmission for the Metrics Shared Task rte Alves, Chrysoula Zerva, Ana C. Farinha, Coheur, André F. T. Martins	[ACL Anthology, poster]
Ricardo Rei, Marcos Treviso, Nuno M.	omission for the Quality Estimation Shared Task Guerreiro, Chrysoula Zerva, Ana C. Farinha, Christine Maroti, va, Alon Lavie, Luisa Coheur, André F. T. Martins	[ACL Anthology]
•	babel-IST 2021 Submission for the Metrics Shared Task a Zerva, Daan van Stigt, Craig Stewart, Pedro G. Ramos, ins, Alon Lavie	[ACL Anthology]
Char-RNN and Active Learning for Taisiya Glushkova, Ekaterina Artemo CICLing 2019, published in Springer Le	va	[arXiv]
Skills		
Programming languages: Tools: Main libraries: Languages:	Python , R, C++, HTML, CSS, LATEX Jupyter Notebook, Google Colab, git, bash numpy, pandas, matplotlib, scipy, scikit-learn, keras, pytorch, tenglish(Advanced), Russian(Native), German(A2), Portuguese	
Teaching		
Instituto Superior Técnico Teaching Assistant for Deep Learning course		Lisbon, Portugal Nov 2021 – Feb 2022
HSE University Teaching Assistant for NLP course Teaching Assistant for Python course		Moscow, Russia Sep 2018 – Dec 2019 Sep 2016 – Sep 2018
University Projects		
Graduation Thesis (MSc), DaNetQA: a dataset for binary question answering in Russian		2019 – 2020
Coursework, Detecting Uncertain Information in Natural Language Texts		2018 – 2019
Graduation Thesis (BSc) , Character Level Models for Hashtag Segmentation		2017 - 2018
Coursework, Collecting Dictionaries for Sentiment Analysis of Reviews		2016 – 2017
Coursework, Extracting Timestamps from News in English Language		2015 - 2016
Coursework, Extracting Timestamps to	from News in English Language	2015 - 2010
	managing tasks and projects in real time (analogue of Trello)	2015 – 2016 2015 – 2016
	managing tasks and projects in real time (analogue of Trello)	